Finding Aid for Mattie Azalia Willis papers, 1928-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mattie Azalia Willis papers 1928-1970
Willis, Mattie Azalia, 1912-1970.
2 linear ft. and 1 oversize folder
86298 Aa 2; UAm
Battle Creek, Michigan, African American singer and music teacher, member of the Battle Creek Chapter of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Correspondence, newspaper clippings, and other material relating to her professional career, diaries recording daily activities and personal thoughts, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mattie Willis’ daughter, Mrs. Charlotte Graham (donor no. 5030 ) and came to the library in 1971.
The collection is open to research.
Mattie Robbins was born March 2, 1912 in Battle Creek, Michigan. She graduated from Battle Creek High School in 1929 where she was a member of the glee club and school chorus and where she also played the piano. She attended Battle Creek College studying piano, voice, and violin. Music would be her life's work, both as a concert performer, a radio artist, and a lecturer on music to various groups. In 1947, she was guest soloist for the Canadian Emancipation Celebration in Windsor, Ontario. In 1950, she won the Vocal Division of the Kalamazoo Symphony auditions. Mattie Willis (married in 1940 to Albert Willis) was active in various community and civic groups, including the Calhoun Community Action Agency, and the Battle Creek Chapter of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.
She died in December 28, 1970
The collection has been arranged into the following series: Personal / Biographical; Writings, speech notes, compositions; Community activities; and Diaries.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Arts.; Battle Creek (Mich.); Music--Michigan--Battle Creek.; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Battle Creek (Mich.); Teachers--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Singers--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Women singers--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Women teachers--Michigan--Battle Creek.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Women.; Augusta (Mich.)--Theaters.; Barn Theatre (Augusta, Mich.); Battle Creek (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Interiors.; Musicians.; Organs.; Pianos.; Singing.; Theaters--Michigan--Augusta.; Theatrical productions.; Willis, Mattie Azalia, 1912-1970.; Women.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal / Biographical
  - Personal history and reminiscences, 1938 and 1963 (Box 1)
  - Brochures and newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Memorial books from the funeral of Mattie Willis, December 1970 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    (Portraits and informal photographs of Willis, alone and with friends and associates; photographs of theatrical productions in which Willis performed; and photographs of Willis' homes in Battle Creek, Michigan.)
    (see also oversize group photo of MW as part of school group, UAm)
  - Posters for musical performances (Folder UAm)
    (in oversize folder, UAm)
  - Correspondence, 1929-1971 and undated (Box 1)
- Writings, speech notes, compositions
  - "What Music Has Meant to Me" 1959 (Box 1)
  - "American Negro Music and Its Influence in America and Around the World" undated (Box 1)
  - Conference and speech notes, short story, and other miscellanea, undated (Box 1)
  - Battle Creek College term papers, 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - Musical compositions written by Mattie Willis (Box 1)
- Community activities
  - Calhoun Community Action Agency, 1970, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Reorganized Church of Jesus Christ of the Latter Day Saints [Grand Rapids], 1970 (Box 1)
  - Battle Creek chapter of the N.A.A.C.P., 1968 (Box 1)
- Diaries
  - 1928 (Box 1)
    (MW used earlier dated volume)
  - 1930 ? (Box 1)
  - 1931 (Box 1)
  - 1932 (Box 1)
  - 1933 (Box 1)
  - 1944 (Box 1)
  - 1945 (Box 1)
  - 1946 (Box 1)
  - 1947 (Box 1)
  - 1953 (Box 2)
  - 1954, 4 volumes (Box 2)
  - 1955 (Box 2)
  - 1956 (Box 2)
  - 1957 (Box 2)
  - 1958 (Box 2)
  - 1959 (Box 2)
  - 1960 (Box 2)
  - 1961 (Box 2)
  - 1962 (Box 2)
  - 1963 (Box 2)
  - 1964 (Box 2)
  - 1967 (Box 2)